{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In this state, the leader of the “Glass Tax” protest was pardoned by the president, because he was “ignorant of our language.” In another incident in this state, David Bradford organized dissidents after the so-called “Battle of Bower Hill.” Fries’s Rebellion took place in this state, as did an earlier action protesting a controversial 1791 tax favored by Alexander Hamilton. George Washington personally led militia into, for ten points, what state to put down the Whiskey Rebellion?",
      "answer": "Commonwealth of Pennsylvania A"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country clashed with the U.S. during the Venezuelan crisis of Grover Cleveland’s presidency. Historians believe the late 19th century was the time of the “Great Rapprochement” between this country and the U.S. After the U.S. Civil War, this country resolved the Alabama claims with the U.S. and signed the Hay-Pauncefote Treaty. For ten points, name this European country which, as a result of actions like these, began forming the “Special Relationship” with the U.S.",
      "answer": [
        "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland",
        "UK, Britain,",
        "England"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This party fractured over the issue of foreign debt, leading to a break from the Democratic Current. R This party was formed in the Maximato period by Plutarco El´ıas Calles as the National Revolutionary Party. The “Hashtag YoSoy132” student movement protested against this party after it won a 2012 election against the PRD. This party held its nation’s presidency every year from 1928 to 2000, but only under Enrique Pen˜a Nieto since then. For ten points, name this Mexican political party.",
      "answer": [
        "Institutional Revolutionary Party",
        "PRI,",
        "Partido Revolucionario Institucional"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A schoolteacher who helped form this group was assassinated in 1949 after Prime Minister Nokrashy D Pasha was slain. A member of this group, Sayyid Qutb [KUT-buh], wrote a 30-volume commentary on Islam that indirectly influenced Osama Bin Laden. Founded in Ismailia by Hassan al-Banna, this group’s slogan is “Islam is the Solution.” President Nasser banned, for ten points, what Sunni Islamic movement in Egypt that rose to power during the 2012 Arab Spring under Mohamed Morsi?",
      "answer": [
        "Muslim Brotherhood",
        "Society of the Muslim Brothers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Bob Herbert claimed that this book brought to light “sordid realities that had remained hidden for too long.” Dorr’s Rebellion was a movement that this book’s author claims was part of the “Other Civil War.” This book’s author claims that James K. Polk’s warmongering was opposed by the general populace. The author of this book claimed that he wrote it to provide a “more honest take” than the “fundamental nationalist glorification of country.” For ten points, name this book written by Howard Zinn.",
      "answer": "A People’s History of the United States T"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Valois prince was elected king of this state but returned to France with much of its treasury. This country’s history was marred by a series of invasions and conflicts known as “The Deluge.” This country was created by the Union of Lublin and governed by a bicameral parliament known as the Sejm [SEYM]. This country’s May 3 Constitution was the second codified constitution in the world. For ten points, name F this country which was dismantled into three partitions by Russia, Prussia, and Austria.",
      "answer": "Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth"
    },
    {
      "question": "John Price Buchanan, a governor of this state, faced a Knights of Labor-led uprising relating to the company use of convict labor in the Coal Creek War. A company named for this state that worked in A coal, iron, and railroads later merged with U.S. Steel. Part of the Manhattan Project was located at this state’s Oak Ridge National Laboratory near Knoxville. During the New Deal, FDR proposed a federal corporation to provide electricity named for, for ten points, what Southern state?",
      "answer": "Tennessee"
    },
    {
      "question": "John Quincy Adams noted that this agreement was what “speculative philosophers have imagined as the only legitimate source of government.” William Brewster is thought to have drafted this agreement. John Carver became governor after he was the first to sign this document, which created a “civil Body PolRitick.” William Bradford was among the signers of, for ten points, what governing document of Plymouth Colony, named for the ship on which the Puritans sailed to America?",
      "answer": "Mayflower Compact"
    },
    {
      "question": "A battle with this instrument’s name was won by the Allies in Central Cameroon in 1915. A surveillance software company with this name had its contract with the state of Utah suspended in April, 2020 after ownership’s connections with the KKK were discovered. This instrument was played by Pete Seeger and Earl Scruggs at the Grand Ole Opry. For ten points, name this instrument associated with Dboth traditional African-American music and bluegrass, typically circular with four or five strings.",
      "answer": "Banjo"
    },
    {
      "question": "ThiseventwasinfluencedbyCIApropagandathatattemptedtoempowerCardinalJozsefMindszenty [mind-SENT-ee]. A government in this event issued the “For Freedom and Truth” proclamation. Tensions from this event spilled over to the “Blood in the Water” water polo match at the Melbourne Olympics in the same year. J´anos [YAHN-oash] K´ad´ar was installed as chairman as a result of Soviet intervention in this event. For ten points, name this revolution in which Imre Nagy [NAHZH] tried to withdraw his country from the Warsaw Pact.",
      "answer": [
        "Hungarian Revolution of 1956",
        "Hungarian Uprising T"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One opponent of this event, Thomas Grantham, secured a garrison on the York River. The instigator of this event may have been jealous due to his inabiFlity to enter the Green Spring Circle. John Ingram replaced this event’s leader after he died of dysentery. This event’s participants were angry over a governor’s refusal to adopt a harsh stance against the natives. For ten points, name this 1676 rebellion against Governor William Berkeley during which Jamestown was burned.",
        "answer": "Bacon’s Rebellion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bacon’s Laws, passed as a reaction to Bacon’s Rebellion, were enacted by this representative element of the Virginia General Assembly. A",
        "answer": "House of Burgesses"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ArulerofthisnamewassupposedlyraisedbyaSassaniankingandappointedNestoriusasArchbishop of Constantinople. Another ruler of this name defeated the usurper Magnus Maximus at the Battle of the Save [SAH-vuh] and appointed Arbogast as magister militum. One man with this name was made co-emperor of the East following Valens’s death at Adrianople. For ten points, give this name shared by two Roman emperors in the 4th and 5th centuries.",
        "answer": [
          "Theodosius",
          "Theodosius I",
          "Theodosius II R"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Theodosius I was excommunicated for his massacre against the inhabitants of this city, perhaps better known for two epistles of the Apostle Paul.",
        "answer": [
          "Thessalonica",
          "Thessaloniki"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this city, the “senator-maker”, Alexander McKenzie, illegally seized mines. This city was the landing spot of the Black Wolf Squadron. Curtis Welch tended to quarantined citizens in this city during a diphtheria outbreak. Gunnar Kaasen finished an essential supplies mission to this city during which D Leonhard Seppala and Togo ran the longest leg. The Great Race of Mercy resupplied medicine to this city on the Seward Peninsula. For ten points, the dog Balto helped save what Alaskan city in 1925?",
        "answer": "Nome, Alaska"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The icebound Seward Peninsula could only be reached by this trail, the site of an annual sled dog race since 1973.",
        "answer": "Iditarod Trail T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Beppu hid this leader’s head after he took a mortal wound to the femur. This leader accepted Katsu Kaishu’s surrender. This founder of the Shigakko military academies resigned in protest after his country decided in the Seikanron debate not to send him to Korea. One of this leader’s campaigns was halted when he failed to take Kumamoto Castle, and he died at the Battle of Shiroyama. For ten points, name F this leader who led the Satsuma Rebellion, known as “the last true samurai.”",
        "answer": [
          "Saigo Takamori",
          "Saigo Kokichi,",
          "Saigo Nanshu"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After Takamori’s mortal injury at Shiroyama, he committed this form of ritual suicide.",
        "answer": [
          "Seppuku",
          "Harakiri",
          "other similar pronunciations,"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Since 1957, the Nizari holder of this title has been Aga Khan IV. American activist and philosopher Amina Wadud has received death threats for her assertion that women can hold this title. The Sevener and Twelver doctrines refer to the number of people believed to have held this title. According to Shia doctrine, the 12th holder of this title is subject to “The Occultation” and will return as the Mahdi. For ten points, name this title, which in Sunni Islam refers to the prayer leaders in mosques.",
        "answer": "Imam"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Those in Islam who hold to belief in the Mahdi believe that he will return at the end of times witRh this prophet who was sent with a new revelation, called the Injil.",
        "answer": [
          "Isa ibn Maryam",
          "Jesus, son of Mary"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this country discredited China’s “three worlds” interpretation of communism in his book Imperialism and the Revolution. A man born with the name Ahmet Muhtar Zogolli faced an invasion led by Benito Mussolini in 1939 while serving as this country’s king. Home to the port city of Durr¨es, during World War Two, this country was led by Prime Minister Enver Hoxha [HOADJ-uh]. For ten points, name this Balkan country on the eastern shore of the Adriatic Sea. D",
        "answer": "Republic of Albania"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1939, Mussolini declared Albania an Italian protectorate under the rule of this king of Italy who abdicated in 1946.",
        "answer": "Victor Emmanuel III T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist invented signal-flow graphs while working at Bell Labs during World War Two. Basing his work on a minimax procedure and positional evaluation, this scientist outlined one of the first computer programs for playing chess. Along with Nyquist, this American names the sampling theorem in digital signal processing. This mathematician published a landmark paper in 1948 titled “A Mathematical F Theory of Communication.” For ten points, name this “father of information theory.”",
        "answer": "Claude Shannon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1985, Claude Shannon won Japan’s highest private award for achievement in the arts and sciences, an award named for this city that served as the seat of the imperial court for eleven centuries.",
        "answer": "Kyoto City A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The arrival at this battle of a brigade led by John Gregg prompted one general to exclaim, “The Texans always move them!” Four miles from where Stonewall Jackson had been shot at Chancellorsville, James Longstreet was injured by friendly fire at this battle. Ending a day before the Battle of Spotsylvania Courthouse, this battle was the first in Lee’s Overland Campaign. For ten points, name this Civil War battle, named after the difficult terrain on which it was fought.",
        "answer": "Battle of the Wilderness"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the key generals at the Battle of the Wilderness was this man who narrowly lost the 1880 U.SR. presidential election to James Garfield.",
        "answer": "Winfield Scott Hancock"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Battle of Bunker Hill",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Site of the battle, a Massachusetts city under siege at the time F",
          "answer": "Boston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Body part that Patriots were told to see the “whites of” before they fired",
          "answer": "Eyes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Location at which most of it was fought, southeast of Bunker Hill",
          "answer": "Breed’s Hill A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Post-battle petition to avoid war that was rejected by the British",
          "answer": "Olive Branch Petition"
        },
        {
          "question": "Doctor and revolutionary leader whose death was depicted in a John Trumbull painting",
          "answer": "Joseph Warren"
        },
        {
          "question": "British general who led the assault, afterward named commander-in-chief in North America",
          "answer": "William Howe R"
        },
        {
          "question": "American general who attempted to reform the defense on Bunker Hill",
          "answer": "Israel Putnam"
        },
        {
          "question": "British governor and general who was recalled to England after the battle",
          "answer": "Thomas Gage D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Spartacist uprising",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Soviet faction led by Lenin that the Spartacists emulated F",
          "answer": "Bolsheviks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Marxist political party who launched the uprising, later banned",
          "answer": [
            "Communists Party of Germany",
            "KPD"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Government that replaced the Council of the People’s Deputies, named for the city in which it was founded A",
          "answer": "Weimar Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Female leader who wrote the Junius Pamphlet and was executed after the failure of the uprising",
          "answer": "Rosa Luxemburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nationalist paramilitary units used to suppress the uprising",
          "answer": [
            "Freikorps",
            "Free corps"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Force of unpaid sailors that defeated regular German troops in the Skirmish of the Berlin Schloss R",
          "answer": [
            "Volksmarinedivision",
            "People’s Navy Division"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Spartacist leader, who as a Reichstag member opposed World War One, shot while allegedly trying to escape",
          "answer": "Karl Liebknecht"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Social Democrats who opposed the Spartacists",
          "answer": "Fredrich Ebert D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hong Kong protests",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Banned item used by protesters to conceal their identities F",
          "answer": "Face masks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Protestors feared the erosion of this principle describing the separate governments of Hong Kong and China",
          "answer": [
            "“One country, two systems”",
            "Guo liang zhi"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Object that became a symbol of protests against changes giving Beijing an increased role in elections A",
          "answer": "Umbrella"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese organized crime group believed to have beaten protesters during the 2014 and 2019 protests",
          "answer": [
            "Triads",
            "San he hui"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Law that guarantees Hong Kong’s autonomy until 2047",
          "answer": "Basic Law"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chief executive, sanctioned by the US in 2019 for undermining Hong Kong’s autonomy R",
          "answer": "Carrie Lam"
        },
        {
          "question": "London-based bank whose branches were vandalized after denying service to Spark Alliance",
          "answer": [
            "HSBC Holdings plc",
            "Hong Kong and Shanghai Banking Corporation Limited"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Student activist who led Scholarism during the 2014 protests, later secretary general of Demosisto",
          "answer": "Joshua Wong D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man founded the American Ethnological Society along with John Russell Bartlett. William Crawford wanted this man as his runFning mate in the 1824 election, though this man dropped out. This man was the main negotiator of the Treaty of Ghent, ending the War of 1812. Agitators in the (20 pts)",
        "Whiskey Rebellion were calmed down by this man, who continued his earlier work by serving as the head of New York City’s branch of the (10 pts)",
        "National Bank. For ten points, name this man who served as Secretary of the Treasury for Thomas Jefferson and James Madison, dubbed the “Swiss Founding Father.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Albert Gallatin A"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The central location of this event was enclosed by the Blue Police. This event inspired “Zog nit keyn mol,” sometimes called “Partisan Song,” by Hirsh Glick, a Vilna inmate. In 1970, after placing a wreath at a monument dedicated to the heroes of this event, (20 pts)",
        "Willy Brandt suddenly knelt in front of the monument. The details of this event were collected in the Stroop Report, named for the man who oversaw the (10 pts)",
        "transportation of its victims to Treblinka and other camps. For ten points, name this largest Jewish revolt during World War Two, which occurred in a Polish city."
      ],
      "answer": "Warsaw Ghetto Uprising R"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Koxinga attacked Fort Provintia near this city, which later became the capital of the Tungning Kingdom. The Tapani rebellion against Japanese rule started at the since- demolished Xilai Temple in this city. A short-lived republic in this city invited French engineers to construct the defensive Erkunshen Battery, or (20 pts)",
        "Eternal Golden Castle. This city was built around the Dutch Fort Zeelandia on a sandbar called Taioan, today known as the district of (10 pts)",
        "Anping. The brief Republic of Formosa was declared from, for ten points, what oldest city in Taiwan? DANSWER: Tainan City (4) Singer Dorce Gamalama was criticized for attending the funerals of the perpetrators of this event and for saying she was “certain [they] had gone to heaven.” One perpetrator of this incident struck at a nightclub named Paddy’s Irish Bar twenty seconds before another attack at the Sari Club. The Sanglah (+) Hospital overflowed with victims of this event that killed 202 people. This event was perpetrated by Abu Bakar Bashir’s group, Jemaah Islamiyah, and included an attack on the US Consulate in (*) Denpasar. For ten points, name this series of terrorist attacks in Indonesia."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "2002 Bali bombings",
        "synonyms of “bombings”, such as attacks, killings, etc. T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man depicted three babies pulling on a kite string attached to a key in his painting Benjamin Franklin Drawing Electricity from the Sky. Another of this artist’s works is set in the village of Shackamaxon and features the Lenape tribe resting under an elm tree. Another painting by this man depicts military officers (20 pts)",
        "crowding around their fallen F commander after his wounding in the Battle of the (10 pts)",
        "Plains of Abraham. For ten points, name this American painter of Penn’s Treaty with the Indians and The Death of General Wolfe."
      ],
      "answer": "Benjamin West"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group was weakened when the Engelbrekt rebellion broke out over a diminishing iron trade. Sten Sture the Younger’s opposition to this group was stamped out after Archbishop Gustavus Trolle ordered a massacre of this group’s enemies. This union was A finally dissolved when (20 pts)",
        "Christian II was defeated by Gustav I, marking the beginning of Vasa independence. This union had originally been founded by Margaret I to counteract the influence of the (10 pts)",
        "Hanseatic League. For ten points, identify this medieval union between Denmark, Sweden, and Norway."
      ],
      "answer": "Kalmar Union"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one novel by this author, King Ladislaus Jagiello commands his troops at the Battle of Grunwald in their defeat of the Teutonic knights. Under a pseudonym, this man wrote theRtravel essays Litwos’ Letters From a Journey. In a historical novel by this author of The Knights of the Cross, he inaccurately depicts Tigellinus suggesting that (20 pts)",
        "Nero order the burning of Rome to blame it on the Christians. In that work by this Nobel laureate, Peter asks the title question to an apparition of (10 pts)",
        "Jesus and accepts his martyrdom. For ten points, name this Polish author of Quo Vadis."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Henryk Sienkiewicz",
        "Litwos before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This oil millionaire was central to the establishment of the Mid-Continent Oil and Gas DAssociation. This man was endorsed by Jesse Owens and was the subject of the quote “as Maine goes, so goes Vermont.” Styles Bridges was tapped to be this man’s running mate but was dropped as his name made the ticket sound like a famous (20 pts)",
        "nursery rhyme. George Gallup infamously miscalculated poll results to reflect this man and Frank Knox winning the (10 pts)",
        "1936 presidential election. For ten points, name this man who was defeated in that election by Franklin Delano Roosevelt while serving as governor of Kansas."
      ],
      "answer": "Alfred Landon T"
    }
  ]
}